A Finding Aid to the Bill Barrett Papers, 1930-2013, bulk 1950-2013, in the Archives of American Art AAA.barrbill
Archives of American Art
Bill Barrett papers
bulk 1950-2013
1930-2013
AAA.barrbill
Archives of American Art
8.9 Linear feet
The papers of Bill Barrett measure 8.9 linear feet and date from 1930-2013, with the bulk of the material dating from 1950-2013. The collection consists of biographical material, lectures, exhibition files, scrapbooks, printed material, artwork, sketchbooks, and photographic materials that document Bill Barrett's career as a sculptor and painter.
Barrett, Bill, 1934-
Scope and Contents note
The papers of Bill Barrett measure 8.9 linear feet and date from 1930-2013, with the bulk of the material dating from 1950-2013. The collection consists of biographical material, lectures and a talk, exhibition files, scrapbooks, printed material, artwork, sketchbooks, and photographic materials that document Bill Barrett's career as a sculptor and painter.
Biographical material documents Barrett's awards from Audubon Artists and the Hakone Open Air Museum. Also included is an interview with Bill Barrett. Lectures and a talk consist of recordings on five videocassettes. Four lectures by Barrett were presented in conjunction with exhibition installations featuring his work. There is also a talk about public art given to a local community board in Sarasota, Florida. Exhibition files on nine videocassettes and one videodisc record openings of installations at galleries and the homes of private collectors. Nineteen scrapbooks document Barrett's solo and group exhibitions, public and private commissions as well as teaching positions and speaking engagements from circa 1970-2013.
Printed material includes some laminated display cards advertising Barrett's sculptures, a few reproductions of sculptures, and a monograph on the artist's work. Artwork by Bill Barrett consists of five pencil sketches of sculptures and five drawings that were used as preliminary studies for Barrett's paintings. Thirteen sketchbooks mostly contain preliminary studies for Barrett's sculptures; a few of the sketchbooks are annotated. Photographic materials include slides of artwork from 1959-1979 and a portfolio of digital prints of Bill Barrett's sculptures and paintings.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The collection was donated in 2014 by Bill Barrett.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 8 series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1987-1994 (Boxes 1, 11; 0.1 linear ft.)
Series 2: Lectures and Talk, 1978-1987, 2000-2003 (Box 1; 0.3 linear ft.)
Series 3: Exhibition Files, 1978-2012 (Boxes 1-2; 0.8 linear ft.)
Series 4: Scrapbooks, circa 1930-2013 (Boxes 2-7; 6.1 linear ft.)
Series 5: Printed Material, circa 1990-2011 (Boxes 7-8, 11; 0.2 linear ft.)
Series 6: Artwork, 1971, 1995-2002 (Boxes 8, 11; 0.2 linear ft.)
Series 7: Sketchbooks, circa 1950s-1995 (Boxes 8-9; 1.0 linear ft.)
Series 8: Photographic Materials, 1959-1979, circa 2012-2013 (Box 10; 0.2 linear ft.)
Biographical/Historical note
Bill Barrett (1934-) is a sculptor and painter in New York and New Mexico.
Harry Stanford Barrett IV, known as Bill Barrett was born in Los Angeles, California in 1934. His father, Stan Barrett was a painter and teacher; his mother, Theodora Barrett was a homemaker. Bill Barrett attended the University of Michigan from 1958-1960 receiving a Bachelor of Science in Design, a Master in Science, and a Master of Fine Arts in Sculpture. By the late 1950's, Barrett had gained recognition for his welded sculptural works. His work was included in group shows at the Indiana Art Center and the Detroit Institute of Arts; his sculptures were acquired by museums and universities for their collections. During this period, Barrett held teaching positions at the Cleveland Institute of Art (1963-1964), the University of Michigan (1960-1968), and City College of New York (1970).
Bill Barrett had his first exhibition in New York at the Jason Gallery in 1967. By the 1970's, Barrett had set up a studio in New York City's Tribeca neighborhood and his fabricated aluminum sculptures were featured in the 1970 Whitney Biennial as well as in group exhibitions at the 10 Downtown, Andre Emmerich Gallery, and the Benson Gallery. In the 1980s, Bill Barrett's style evolved from abstract, geometric shapes to more fluid, expressive designs. Also, the Shidoni Foundry in New Mexico was overseeing the fabrication of Barrett's larger sculptural works. He was invited by Debora Hicks, daughter of the Foundry's owner, Tom Hicks to show his work at the Shidoni Sculpture Gardens, and since then, he has been a regular exhibitor at Shidoni. In 1992, Bill Barrett and Debora Hicks married, setting up a home and studio in New Mexico. Influenced by the landscape of New Mexico, Bill Barrett returned to painting and he has had several exhibitions that featured both his paintings and sculptures. In recent years, Barrett also designs jewelry.
Bill Barrett has participated in over 100 exhibitions held at galleries, museums, and other arts venues in the United States, Europe, and Japan. He has received numerous commissions to design both indoor and outdoor sculptures from individuals, corporations, academic institutions, local and state governments. Barrett has served as the President of the Sculptors Guild and he is a member of the Century Club and the National Arts Club. He has been awarded the Audubon Artists Gold Medal of Honor in Sculpture, the Chaim Gross Foundation Award for Audubon Artists, the Hakone Open Air Museum Award in Tokyo, and the Reynolds Memorial Award for Sculpture.
Bill Barrett has two sons and a daughter from a previous marriage. He and Debora Hicks Barrett divide their time between New York and New Mexico.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original material requires an appointment. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Audubon Artists (New York, N.Y.).; Hakone Bijutsukan.; Interviews; Painters--New Mexico--Santa Fe; Painters--New York (State)--New York; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Sculptors--New Mexico--Santa Fe; Sculptors--New York (State)--New York; Sketchbooks; Sketches; Video recordings
- Biographical Material, 1987-1994; Series 1; 0.1 Linear feet Boxes 1, 11
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical material includes awards from Audubon Artists, Chaim Gross Foundation, and the Hakone Open Air Museum. There is also a recording of an interview with Bill Barrett conducted in 1987 on one videocassette; the interviewer is unidentified. Biographical materials can also be found in Series 4: Scrapbooks.
  Arrangement note
  Items are arranged by subject and filed in chronological order.
  - Interview with Bill Barrett, 1987; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Award Plaque from the Hakone Open Air Museum, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Oversized material housed in Box 11
  - Title Plates from Audubon Artists, Chaim Gross Foundation Award, 1987; 1992 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Audubon Artists, Medals of Honor, 1990; 1994 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Oversized Award Plaque from the Hakone Open Air Museum from Box 1, Folder 2, 1987 (Box 11)
- Lectures and Talk, 1978-1987; 2000-2003; Series 2; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1
  This series consists of recordings on five videocassettes. Included are four lectures by Bill Barrett that were given in conjunction with exhibitions featuring his work. Barrett's talk, "Art and Public Places" was presented to community board members in Sarasota, Florida.
  This series is arranged in chronological order.
  - Lecture at Cuyahoga Community College (1978 May 3), 1984-1985; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Includes recordings of exhibitions at Schulman Sculpture Garden, White Plains, New York and Bellevue Hospital Sculpture Garden, New York.
  - Lecture at Goddard Center, Installation of "El Grande", 1987; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "The Grounds for Sculpture Lecture Series", 2000; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Lecture and Slide Presentation for "The Grounds for Sculpture Lecture Series", 2000; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Talk -- "Art in Public Places", 2003; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Exhibition Files, 1978-2012; Series 3; 0.8 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  This series consists of 9 videocassette recordings of several installation openings held at galleries and at the private homes of collectors. The video recordings were made by Bill Barrett for his personal use. Additional documentation on exhibitions can be found in Series 4: Scrapbooks.
  - Larrabee Group - Bill Barrett (1978 May 3), 2006; 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Includes pop-up exhibition announcement
  - Lux Installation, 1984; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Installation of Tres Grande, Repose, and Coupling ( Rendezvous), Bellevue Hospital Sculpture Garden (1985 March 17), 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Baille Merengue, 1989; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Shidoni Gallery Opening and Party (1990 September 28), 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - L.A. Baroque Installation (1992 February), 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Saggamore Party, Installation at Barry Head's House (1993 May 20), 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Dersh's Installation (1993 May 31) and The Cline Gallery Opening (1993 July 2), 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Nardin Gallery, 1997; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Lew Allen Gallery Opening and Barrett Studio and Sculpture Garden, 2012; 2 Videodiscs (DVD) Duplicates (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Scrapbooks, circa 1930-2013; Series 4; 6.1 Linear feet Boxes 2-7
  Scrapbooks document Barrett's professional activities as a sculptor, painter, educator, and lecturer. Files include a variety of materials, e.g., biographical material, correspondence, proposals, lists, sales information, contracts and agreements, sketches, schematic diagrams, and printed material. Also included are photographs, slides, and negatives of artwork.
  Biographical material includes awards and personal photographs of Barrett as a child and youth as well as photographs of his family members. Business related correspondence includes letters with museums, galleries, and arts venues relating to proposed projects, scheduling of exhibitions, and requests to lecture and teach. Among the printed materials are press releases, clippings, reviews of Barrett's work, exhibition catalogs, brochures, invitations, and gallery guides. Many of the photographs are annotated with the title, date, and owner of the work.
  Scrapbooks were received in three-ring binders and the original order of the material has been maintained. Scrapbooks are arranged in chronological order.
  - Scrapbook, "1964", circa 1950-1964; circa 1930 (Box 2, Folder 7-10)
  - Scrapbook, "1965-1969", 1964-1969 (Box 3, Folder 1-4)
  - Scrapbook, "1970-1976", 1969-1976; 2002 (Box 3, Folder 5-7)
  - Scrapbook, "1977-1978", circa 1977-1979 (Box 3, Folder 8-9)
  - Scrapbook, "1979" (Box 3, Folder 10-12)
  - Scrapbook, "1980" (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook, "1981-1982", 1981-1986 (Box 4, Folder 2-5)
  - Scrapbook, "1983-1986", 1982-1987 (Box 4, Folder 6-9)
  - Scrapbook, "1987-1989" (Box 4, Folder 10-12)
  - Scrapbook, "1987-1989", 1988-1989 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
  - Scrapbook, "1990-1991", 1990-1992 (Box 5, Folder 3-6)
  - Scrapbook, "1992-1994", 1992-1995 (Box 5, Folder 7-10)
  - Scrapbook, "1995-1996" (Box 5, Folder 11-14)
  - Scrapbook, "1997-1998" (Box 6, Folder 1-4)
  - Scrapbook, "1999", 1998-2000 (Box 6, Folder 5-7)
  - Scrapbook, "2000" (Box 6, Folder 8-10)
  - Scrapbook, "2001", 2001-2003 (Box 6, Folder 11-13)
  - Scrapbook, "2001" (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook, "2002", 2001-2002 (Box 7, Folder 2-4)
  - Scrapbook, "2003-2009", 2002-2009; Includes 1 videodisc (DVD) (Box 7, Folder 5-9)
  - Scrapbook, "2010-2013", 2006-2013 (Box 7, Folder 10-12)
- Printed Material, circa 1990-2011; Series 5; 0.2 Linear feet Boxes 7-8, 11
  This series includes laminated display cards advertising Barrett's sculptures in Art in America and Art News. A file on the musical dedication of Bill Barrett's painting Polyphonic Abstraction at the University of Iowa includes printed material, programs, an invitation, and a musical score. Also included is a recording of the concert on 1 sound disc. Additional printed material can be found in Series 4: Scrapbooks.
  Files are arranged by format and thereafter in chronological order.
  - Advertising Display Cards, undated; 1994-circa 2008 (Box 7, Folder 13-14)
  - Reproductions of Sculptures, circa 1990-circa 2008 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Book, Bill Barrett: Evolution of a Sculptor, 2003 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Poster Board - Dedication of Polyphonic Abstraction, 2011; Includes 1 sound disc (CD); oversized material housed in Box 11 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Oversized Book, Bill Barrett: Evolution of a Sculptor from Box 8, Folder 2, 2003 (Box 11)
  - Oversized Poster Board - Dedication of Polyphonic Abstraction from Box 8, Folder 3, 2011 (Box 11)
- Artwork, 1995-2002; 1971; Series 6; 0.2 Linear feet Boxes 8, 11
  Artwork by Bill Barrett consists of five pencil sketches sealed in Plexiglas, including sketches of his Circle Series and Manhattan Series. Also found are five preliminary drawings of paintings done in ink, crayon, and color pencils. Additional sketches can also be found in Series 4: Scrapbooks.
  Files are arranged in chronological order.
  - Sketches, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 4-8)
  - Drawings - Studies for Paintings, 1995-2002 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Oversized Drawings from Box 8, Folder 9, 1995-2001 (Box 11)
- Sketchbooks, circa 1950s-1995; Series 7; 1 Linear feet Boxes 8-9
  Thirteen sketchbooks include preliminary drawings of sculptures as well as sketches of portraits and landscapes. There are a few sketches of the home of Bill Barrett's father, Stan Barrett in Sewanee, Tennesse, where he was an artist-in-residence at the University of the South. Interspersed among the pages are loose sketches and Barrett's notes on preserving the finish of fabricated sculptures and instructions for the casting and coloring of brasses. Some of the sketches are annotated with sales prices.
  Sketchbooks are arranged in chronological order.
  - Sketchbook 1, circa 1950s-circa 1970s (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Sketchbook 2, circa 1960-circa 1970 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Sketchbook 3, circa 1960-circa 1970 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Sketchbook 4, circa 1960-circa 1970 (Box 8, Folder 13-14)
  - Sketchbook 5, circa 1970-circa 1980 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Sketchbook 6, circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 8, Folder 16-17)
  - Sketchbook 7, circa 1976 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Sketchbook 8, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Sketchbook 1, circa 1979 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Sketchbook 2, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Sketchbook 3, circa 1990s (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Sketchbook 4, circa 1990s (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Sketchbook 5, 1995 (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Photographic Materials, 1959-1979; circa 2012-2013; Series 8; 0.2 Linear feet Box 10
  Photographic materials include slides of Barrett's sculptures from 1959-1979. The portfolio contains digital prints of Barrett's work. Researchers can also find photographs and slides in Series 4: Scrapbooks.
  This series is arranged by format, in chronological order.
  - Slides of Artwork, "1950s-1960s", 1959-1969 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Slides of Artwork, "1969-1979", 1968-1979 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Bill Barrett, Portfolio Archive, circa 2012-2013 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    This series is arranged by format, in chronological order. Researchers can also find photographs and slides in Series 4: Scrapbooks.